Finding Aid for Church Women United In Michigan records, 1929-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Church Women United In Michigan records 1929-2011
Church Women United in Michigan.
8580 Ba 2; BA Outsize
Interdenominational church women's organization. Histories, programs, office files, scrapbooks, and photographs of activities.
8 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the organization in 1980 (donor no. 6474 ). Periodic additions have been received since then, including one made in 1993 by Mrs. Elvira Vogel (donor no. 7908 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
Church Women United in Michigan grew out of efforts of various Protestant women's organizations to establish an annual day of prayer. As interdenominational ties grew, the value of a permanent coordinating body was seen. In 1929, four local interdenominational women's organizations and about forty World Day of Prayer groups formed the Michigan Council of Federated Church Women. The Michigan group was the first state organization under the new National Council of Federated Church Women. Between 1951 and 1953, the group changed its name to United Church Women of Michigan, and in 1967 they became Church Women United in Michigan. This series of name changes appears to have followed national trends toward an emphasis on unity.
In addition to World Day of Prayer, the organization came to support social reforms, including better race relations and service projects designed to aid the economically underprivileged worldwide. In 1940, the organization appears to have expanded the number of Protestant denominations within its membership. In 1967, the first official links with Eastern Orthodox and Catholic women's organizations were formed.
The records of Church Women United in Michigan (CWUMI) reflect only a part of the organization's history. No primary materials exist prior to 1948, and the existing material created between 1948 and 1954 is very sketchy. Documentation is richest starting the 1960s. Material from this era includes minutes of CWUMI executive and annual meetings, material relating to committees and committee reports, bylaws, correspondence of CWUMI presidents, periodical publications, files relating to projects and activities, material related to CWUMI local groups, and lists of member organizations.
Subjects:
Church Women United in Michigan.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Women--Religious life--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Church Women United in Michigan.; Women--Organizations.; Women--Spiritual life.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Chronological files
  - 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964
    - General (Box 1)
    - Lists (Box 1)
  - 1965
    - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Lists (Box 1)
  - 1966
    - Ecumenical Campus Center (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Lists (Box 1)
  - 1967
    - General (Box 1)
    - Lists and maps (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976
    - General, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Notebook (Box 1)
    - Wholeways Workshop (Box 1)
  - 1977
    - General, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Lists (Box 2)
    - Notebooks (Box 2)
    - Reports (Box 2)
  - 1978
    - General (Box 2)
    - Lists (Box 2)
    - Reports (Box 2)
    - Workbook (Box 2)
  - 1979 (Box 2)
  - 1980s (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - By date
    - 1968 (Box 2)
    - 1969 (Box 2)
    - 1975 (Box 2)
    - 1976 (Box 2)
    - 1977 (Box 2)
    - 1978, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
  - Negatives, 197?-1987 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 197?-1979 (Box 2)
  - Slides 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - 50th Jubilee slides 1979 (Box 2)
- Sound recordings
  - 40th Anniversary, 1 audiocassettes (Box 2)
  - 50th anniversary, 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
  - Interviews with past presidents and published history prepared for 50th Anniversary, 3 audiocassettes (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks
  - 1929-1954 (Volume 1)
  - 1954-1959 (Box 3)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - 1962-1964 (Box 3)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - 1967-1969 (Box 3)
  - 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - 1979 (Box 6)
- Topical and Administrative files
  - Annual Assembly Programs
    - 1948-1954 (Box 4)
    - 1965-1969 (Box 4)
    - 1970-1974 (Box 4)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 4)
    - 1981-1991 (Box 4)
    - 1993-1995 (Box 7)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 7)
    - 1999-2000 (Box 7)
    - 2001-2004 (Box 7)
    - 2005-2007 (Box 7)
    - 2009-2011 (Box 7)
  - Annual Meeting 1974-2006 with gaps (Box 4)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1961-1991, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1992-1993, 1995-2011, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Area Meetings
    - 1998-2000 (Box 7)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 7)
    - 2004 (Box 7)
    - 2006 (Box 7)
    - 2008-2009, 2011 (Box 7)
  - Bridge Project 1985-1988 (Box 4)
  - Bylaws
    - 1967-1986 (Box 4)
    - 1992-1998, 2008 (Box 4)
  - Contracts (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - General 1979-1983 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Church Woman, newsletter (Box 4)
    - With National 1972-1973, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
    - From Former State Presidents
      - 1980-1988 (Box 4)
      - 1997-2009 (with gaps) (Box 8)
  - Cuba Exchange Project (Box 7)
    (files include photographs)
    - Baby Daniel (Box 7)
    - Cuba Exchange Project Files (Box 7)
    - Trips 2000-2004, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Denominational Representative (Box 4)
  - Directories 1962-1993, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Directories 1994-2001, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Ecumenical Center and International Residence (Box 7)
  - Executive board and state board meetings
    - 1967, 1970-1989, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - 1990-2008, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Executive committee meeting minutes
    (includes reports of other committees)
    - 1962-1967 (Box 4)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 4)
    - 1981-1999 (Box 4)
  - Executive declaration from Governor Milliken 1982 (Box 4)
  - Fact sheets 1972-1976 (Box 4)
  - Healthcare 1992-1994 (Box 8)
    - Ethical Choices (Box 8)
    - Healthcare Reform (Box 8)
    - Project Report (Box 8)
  - Histories (1954 1969, 1979, 1981 2009) (Box 5)
  - Michigan Church Woman newsletter, 1966-1992, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Michigan Church Woman newsletter, 1993-2010, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Leadership Council 1997-2007 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Ecumenical Forum (Box 8)
  - Native American Task Force 1979, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Newsletters 1976-1981 (local units only) (Box 5)
  - Nominating Committee (Box 5)
  - President's letters
    - Mary Willoughby, ?-1971 (Box 5)
    - Verna Johnson 1971-1973 (Box 5)
    - Trudy Gomer 1973-1976 (Box 5)
    - Nina Klaudt 1976-1979 (Box 5)
    - Pat Brown 1979-1982 (Box 5)
    - Helen Hokenson 1983-1985 (Box 5)
    - Malinda Waltz 1997-1999, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Regional Assembly (Box 8)
  - Resolutions passed 1962-1983 (Box 5)
  - Social Issues
    - Christian Causeway (Box 5)
    - Ecumenical Action (Box 5)
    - Ecumenical Campus Center, University of Michigan (Box 5)
    - Fund for Fifth Decade (Box 5)
    - International Year of the Child (Box 5)
    - Michigan International Council (Box 5)
    - Michigan People's Platform (Box 5)
    - Michigan Women's Commission (Box 5)
    - Michigan Women for Highway Safety (Box 5)
    - Native American Advocacy Committee (Box 5)
    - United Nations (Box 5)
      (includes photographs)
    - World Day of Prayer (Box 5)
  - Treasurer's reports 1970-1999 (Box 5)
  - Valiant Women award
    - 1984-1992 (Box 5)
    - 1993-2011, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Obituaries (Box 8)
  - Women in Community Service (Box 8)
  - Worldwide Family Initiative (Box 8)
  - Youth Ecumenical Award 1996-1999 (Box 8)
    (include photographs)
  - Workbooks 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Workshop planning/outline, handouts (Box 5)
  - Yearbooks
    - Detroit 1975-1988 (Box 5)
    - Local units (Box 5)